<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brontologia sacra: The voice of the glorious God in the thunder: explained and applyed in a sermon uttered by a minister of the Gospel in a lecture unto an assembly of Christians abroad, at the very same time when the thunder was by the permission and providence of God falling upon his own house at home. : Whereunto are added some reflections formed on the Lords-Day following by the voices of thunders, upon the great things which the great God is now doing in the world. : A discourse useful for all men at all times, but especially intended for an entertainment in the hours of thunder.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88921</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097844</idno>
  <idno type="VID">171426</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240899480</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">45097844</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171426)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2573:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Brontologia sacra: The voice of the glorious God in the thunder: explained and applyed in a sermon uttered by a minister of the Gospel in a lecture unto an assembly of Christians abroad, at the very same time when the thunder was by the permission and providence of God falling upon his own house at home. : Whereunto are added some reflections formed on the Lords-Day following by the voices of thunders, upon the great things which the great God is now doing in the world. : A discourse useful for all men at all times, but especially intended for an entertainment in the hours of thunder.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Astwood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cotton Mather by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks p. 9-10.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, American --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Congregational churches --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171426:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171426:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Brontologia Sacra:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE VOICE OF THE Glorious GOD IN THE THUNDER: Explained and Applyed In a Sermon uttered by a Minister of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel in a Lecture unto an Assembly of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians abroad, at the very same time when the Thunder was by the Permission and Providence of God falling upon his own House at home.</p>
            <p>Whereto are added Some Reflections formed on the Lords-Day following by the Voices of Thunders, upon the great things which the great God is now a doing in the World.</p>
            <p>A Discourse useful for all Men at all times, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally intended for an Entertainment in the Hours of <hi>Thunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Astwood,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:171426:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171426:3"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THe Author of the Ensuing Meditations, is willing to have nothing further known, either of <hi>him,</hi> or of <hi>them,</hi> save this, That being at <hi>Prayer</hi> before a <hi>Sermon,</hi> in a little Assembly of Christians, the sudden rise of a <hi>Thunder-storm,</hi> was the Occasion of his feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a strange and a strong <hi>Impression</hi> upon his mind, unto this purpose; <hi>Lay aside what you had prepared for this Auditory, speak to them on the Voice of the Glorious God in the Thunder, you shall not want Assistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> He could not withstand this <hi>Impressio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but ventured upon an extemporaneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the <hi>Thunder.</hi> Now, the thing which made this Digression remarkable, was, that at the very same Instant when he was thus driven to <hi>this Theme,</hi> the <hi>Thunder</hi> was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the God of Heaven to fall with very <hi>tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> tho' no <hi>killing</hi> Effects, upon his <hi>own House.</hi> The Hearers, I suppose, found a sensible Edge given to these <hi>Meditations,</hi> by the wondrous <hi>Timing</hi> of them; and altho' no doubt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would have digested them with more exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, had they not been altogethar like the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171426:4"/>that produced them, <hi>sudden,</hi> yet these Notes taken of them are perhaps not so utterly undigested, as to be wholly useless unto a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposed Reader. Ʋnto these, the Reader will find added, the Notes of a Sermon preached by the same Author unto a very great Congregation on the <hi>Lords-Day</hi> following; and inasmuch as I could never learn that he had written his own Sermon, we must be content with such more broken passages as were taken from his mouth in the time of their Delivery.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Thunder</hi> being a thing that often enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains us, it was thought that it would be no Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>service unto the Church of God, if a few such <hi>Reflections</hi> were offered unto the publick for the entertainment of the serious. When,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ipse Pater media Nimborum in nocte Corus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Fulmina molitur dextrâ quo maxima motu Terra tremit, fugere ferae, &amp; mortalia Corda per gentes humilis stravit pavor.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171426:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Meditations</hi> UPON THUNDER. Uttered <hi>September</hi> 12. 1694.</head>
            <p>OBserving that by the <hi>Thunder-storm,</hi> just now begun, you are, many of you, thrown into a Consternation, which perhaps may indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose you to mind any thing but the <hi>Thunder,</hi> I shall altogether lay aside the <hi>Meditations</hi> wherewith I came hither purposing to entertain you, and I shall with the Leave and Help of your God, who is now speaking, treat you with some sudden <hi>Meditations</hi> upon the <hi>Thunder</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>Christians, you shall shall now go along with me unto the <hi>Twenty-Ninth Psalm,</hi> in the <hi>Third Verse</hi> whereof you shall find these Words,
<q>The Voice of the Lord is upon the Waters, the God of Glory Thundereth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now let not your Attention to the <hi>Thunder</hi> at this Instant <hi>abroad,</hi> interrupt your further Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Greater and Louder <hi>Thunder</hi> here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171426:5"/>the <hi>Voice of God</hi> in this <hi>Book</hi> is far beyond that <hi>Voice,</hi> which is now making its <hi>rapid peals</hi> in the <hi>Sky.</hi> This <hi>Voice</hi> is more articulate than <hi>that,</hi> yea, by <hi>this</hi> Voice <hi>that</hi> becomes articulate, give unto <hi>both</hi> your <hi>earnest Heed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Remember, that while <hi>Elihu</hi> was, as I now am, speaking at a <hi>Private Meeting</hi> of some Godly Men, at <hi>that</hi> very Time, as at <hi>this,</hi> 'tis by some Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters concieved, it <hi>Thundred;</hi> and at the same Time, that <hi>Man</hi> of God, fell into a Discourse up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in the <hi>Thunder. Then</hi> 'twas that he said, in <hi>Job</hi> 37. <hi>beg. At this my Heart tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and is moved out of his place: Hear attentively, the Noise of his voice, and the sound that goeth out of his Mouth. He directeth it under the whole Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and his Lightning unto the ends of the Earth; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it a Voice roareth, he Thundreth with the Voice of his Excellency; and he will not stay them, when his Voice is heard; God Thundreth marvellously with his Voice; great things doth he, which we cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You then will not count it <hi>improper,</hi> and I hope our Common Lord will make it not <hi>unuseful,</hi> if I so far imitate the Example, as to offer you in this Juncture an <hi>Essay,</hi> at explaining the <hi>Voice</hi> of God, in that very <hi>Thunder,</hi> which is just now beginning to Alarum our Thoughts; and this the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Text which we have now read seems to be fetched from those very Words of <hi>Elihu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have before us a <hi>Psalm</hi> composed by a Great <hi>Servant</hi> and <hi>Singer</hi> of the Lord, probably at a time tempestuous by <hi>Thunders,</hi> and composed that it might be employed among the People of God at such a Time. You see how conveniently it may at <hi>this time,</hi> give a Text unto us.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171426:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>Sons</hi> of such <hi>Eminent Patriarchs</hi> as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Jaoob,</hi> are here called upon to give <hi>Glory</hi> unto the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> and this both for his Works of <hi>Nature</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> and for his Works of <hi>Grace</hi> in the <hi>Church:</hi> And among his Works of <hi>Nature,</hi> some done in the <hi>lower-Heaven,</hi> namely, the <hi>Thunders,</hi> are singled out, as the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Occasions for our praising of him. But, If <hi>Angels</hi> may be meant by <hi>the Sons of the mighty,</hi> thus addressed, their own frequent Concernment and Improvement in the producing of <hi>Thunders</hi> gives yet a further <hi>Emphasis</hi> unto this Invitation.</p>
            <p>About the <hi>Thunder,</hi> we have two Remarks in the Words now read unto us:</p>
            <p>First, We have the <hi>place</hi> of it. It is among the <hi>Waters;</hi> that is, in the <hi>Rainy Clouds.</hi> The <hi>Aqueous particles</hi> daily fetched up from the <hi>Earth</hi> and the <hi>Sea</hi> into the Regions of the <hi>Air,</hi> are a Vast advantage to our Quarters of the Creation. The Emptying, the Refreshing, the proportioning of many parts in the Creation, by their perpetual <hi>Distillation,</hi> is justly to be reckoned among Infallible Demonstrations, to prove as well the <hi>Providence</hi> as the <hi>Existence</hi> of the <hi>Great God, who formed all things.</hi> For this cause this thing is well worthy of the Figure which it makes in the <hi>History</hi> of the <hi>Creation;</hi> tho' it had not been there introduced, which probably it is as <hi>Figurative</hi> of that Age, wherein God separated from the rest of the World a Number of People in the Patriarchal Families, whom He called up into a <hi>Church-State;</hi> but so small a Number, that in Comparison to the rest, they were no more than the <hi>Clouds</hi> are unto the <hi>Seas.</hi> This now is <hi>the Secret place of Thunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, We have the <hi>Cause</hi> of it, this is <hi>The Lord, the God of Glory;</hi> Or, the Lord, who is the Glorious God.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171426:6"/>
            <p>It is the Duty of a <hi>Minister</hi> to <hi>Watch</hi> for Seasons, wherein, and whereby the Word of God which he is to Preach, may be advantaged with a Singular <hi>Energy,</hi> for the <hi>Saving of himself and of them that Hear him.</hi> 'Twill be but a piece of <hi>Ministerial Watchfulness,</hi> for the to bring you certain Words of God this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, unto which the Terrible <hi>Thunder</hi> now happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may be subservent with a more than ordinary Penetrancy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sirs,</hi> Be not now <hi>Deaf to Thunder,</hi> but with me make this Observation.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>In the</hi> THUNDER <hi>there is the Voice of the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous GOD.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>There is — [<hi>The Author being arrived hereabouts in his Discourse, a Messenger interrupted him, with Tidings that a</hi> Thunder-clap <hi>had just now fallen upon his own House; and that tho' no Person had been hurt, yet the House had been much Torn, and fill'd with the</hi> Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. <hi>But without breaking off, as had been desired, he thus proceeded.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren,</hi> I am just now informed, That the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorous God</hi> in the <hi>Thunder,</hi> has been very Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately directed unto my self, by a Fall of <hi>Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts</hi> upon my own House, at that very instant, as far as I can judge, that I felt the powerful Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of Heaven upon my own Soul; Inclining and Engaging of me to frame a peculiar <hi>Meditation</hi> upon the <hi>Voice in the Glorious God in the Thunder</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. Instead of being hereby diverted from the <hi>Work</hi> which I have now undertaken, I would <hi>practically</hi> teach you, <hi>That with a mind un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned about the things of this Life, we should never be unfurnished with devout and proper Thoughts on the mind of God in all our Tryals;</hi> and I would hope that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171426:6"/>this <hi>unhappy</hi> Accident will be made <hi>Happy,</hi> at least by procuring yet more of <hi>Edge</hi> to that Attention which the <hi>Voice of God</hi> is to have with you: <hi>To Day if ye will Hear his Voice!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is this Enquiry, which I did but now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to make, and which I am <hi>Now</hi> Concerned more than I was before to make, on this Occasion:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Voice of the Glorious God in the</hi> Thunder?</p>
            <p>First, It is to be premised, as herein Implied and Confessed, that the <hi>Thunder</hi> is the <hi>Work</hi> of the Glorious God. It is true, that the <hi>Thunder</hi> is a <hi>Natural production,</hi> and by the Common Laws of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> it is produced: There is in it a Concourse of divers weighty <hi>Clouds,</hi> Clashing and Breaking one against another, from whence arises a mighty <hi>Sound,</hi> which grows yet more mighty by its Resonancies. The Subtil and Sulpherous <hi>Vapours</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong these <hi>Clouds</hi> take Fire in this Combustion, and <hi>Lightnings</hi> are thence darted forth; which when they are somewhat grosser, are <hi>Fulminated</hi> with an Irresistable Violence upon our Territories. But still who is the Author of those <hi>Laws,</hi> according where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto things are thus <hi>Moved</hi> into <hi>Thunder?</hi> Yea, who is the <hi>First Mover</hi> of them? Christians, 'Tis our Glorious God. There is an Intimation somewhere ['tis in <hi>Psal.</hi> 104.7.] That there was a most early and wondrous use of the <hi>Thunder</hi> in the first <hi>Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the World; but still the <hi>Thunder</hi> it self, and the <hi>Tonitruous</hi> Disposition and Generation with which the Air is Impregnated, was a part of that <hi>Creation.</hi> Well, and whose workmanship is it all? <hi>Ah! Lord, thou hast Created all these things, and for thy pleasure they are, and were Created.</hi> It is also true, that <hi>Angels</hi> may be reconed among the Causes of <hi>Thunders;</hi> and for this Cause, in the sentence of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171426:7"/>the <hi>Psalms,</hi> where they are called <hi>Flames of Fire,</hi> one would have been at a loss whether <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Lightnings</hi> were intended, if the Apostolical Accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation had not Cleared it. But what tho' <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> may have their peculiar <hi>Influence</hi> upon <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> it is but the Influence of an <hi>Instrument;</hi> they are but <hi>Instruments,</hi> Directed, Ordered, Limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Him, who is the <hi>God of Thunders,</hi> and the <hi>Lord of Angels.</hi> Hence the <hi>Thunder</hi> is ascribed unto our God all the Bible over; in the <hi>Scripture of Truth</hi> 'tis called the <hi>Thunder of God,</hi> oftener than I can presently quote unto you. And hence we find the <hi>Thunder</hi> ever now and then, Executing the <hi>purpose</hi> of God: Whose can it be, but the <hi>Thunder of God,</hi> when the <hi>Pleasure</hi> of God has been continually there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by accomplished.</p>
            <p>But I pray, why then should we be <hi>Slavishly Afraid</hi> of the <hi>Thunder?</hi> We are in <hi>Covenant</hi> with that God who makes the <hi>Thunder,</hi> and it is a <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> wherein he is <hi>Our God.</hi> Well, and shall we not now make that Joyful Conclusion, <hi>He is our Own God, and He will Bless us!</hi> Whence then our Amazing Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, when we hear him <hi>Thundering</hi> Terribly in the Heavens over us? As long as the Almighty <hi>Thunderer</hi> is <hi>our Own God,</hi> we need not fear that he will do us any <hi>Hurt</hi> by any of His <hi>Works:</hi> No, He will make <hi>All things work together for our Good.</hi> A Saint may say, <hi>My God will never Hurt me!</hi> Suppose we should be slain by the <hi>Thunder,</hi> we shall but in that <hi>Thunder</hi> of Heaven have a <hi>Great voice from Heaven,</hi> saying to us, <hi>Come up hither!</hi> and setting aside the <hi>unusualness</hi> of the stroke, which makes it seem horrid and uncouth, it were the <hi>easiest way</hi> of <hi>going up</hi> that ever was gon. I say then, ben't <hi>afraid, Ejus est timere qui nolit ad Christum ire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ambrose</hi> in his Treatise of <hi>Angels,</hi> as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171426:7"/>does relate this passage: A Profane Persecutor discovered much Affrightment at the <hi>Thunder</hi> which happened while he was on a Journey, his Pious and Holy Wife then with him, asked him the reason of his being so Affrighted, <hi>Why,</hi> said he, <hi>are not you Afraid?</hi> She replied, <hi>No, Not at all; for I know 'tis the voice of my Heavenly Father; and shall a Child be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of a Kind Fathers Voice?</hi> The Man hereby surprised, made this Conclusion, <hi>sure these</hi> Puritans <hi>have a Divine Principle in them, which the World seeth not; Else they could not have such a Serenity in their Souls, when the rest of the World are filled with dismal Horrors!</hi> Hereupon he went unto Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> bewailing the opposition which he had given unto the Ministry of that Reverend Man, and became a Godly man ever after.</p>
            <p>You know what use to make of the Story, and so I may proceed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is now to be more distinctly Asserted, that the <hi>Thunder</hi> is the <hi>Voice</hi> of the Glorious God; there is a <hi>Voice</hi> of his in this Work of his. If the <hi>Thunder</hi> were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Voice of Jupiter,</hi> in the account of the poor <hi>Pagans,</hi> I am sure it should be accounted <hi>The voice of Jehovah</hi> by us <hi>Christians.</hi> One of the ways whereby God revealed of himself to his Ancient People, was a <hi>Bath Kol,</hi> as they called it, there was a <hi>Voice of Thunder</hi> in it. Sirs, we have what is Equivolent unto a <hi>Bath Kol</hi> this afternoon, in the Significancy which we shall now hear the <hi>Scripture</hi> give unto the <hi>Thunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. One <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorious God</hi> in the <hi>Thunder</hi> is, <hi>that He is a Glorious God who makes the Thunder.</hi> There is the <hi>Marvelous Glory</hi> of God seen in it, when he <hi>Thunders Marvelously.</hi> Thus do these Inferiour and Meteorous <hi>Heavens declare the Glory of God!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171426:8"/>
            <p>The <hi>Power</hi> of God is the <hi>Glory</hi> of God: Now His <hi>Thunder</hi> does proclaim His <hi>Power.</hi> It is said, <hi>the Thunder of His Power, who can Ʋnderstand?</hi> that is, His Powerful Thunder; the <hi>Thunder</hi> gives us to <hi>Ʋnderstand,</hi> that our God is a most <hi>Powerful</hi> One. There is nothing able to <hi>Stand</hi> before those <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi> which are stiled <hi>the Arrows of God;</hi> Castles fall, Metals melt, all flies, when <hi>Hot Thunder-bolts</hi> are scattered upon them. Yea, to speak in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Prophets fulfilled in the <hi>Thunder-storm,</hi> that routed the <hi>Assyrian</hi> Armies, <hi>The Mountains quake, the Hills melt, the Earth is burnt; who can stand before His Indignation? and who can abide in the fierconess of His Anger? His Fury is poured out like Fire, and the Rocks are thrown down by Him. Suetonius,</hi> I think 'tis, who tells us, That the Haughty and Profane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Caligula,</hi> would yet shrink and shake, and cover his Head at the least <hi>Thunder,</hi> and run to hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self under a Bed. This truly is the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Thunder, Let the proudest Sinners tremble to Rebel any more against a God, who can thus discomfit them with shooting out his Lightnings upon them: Sinners, Where can you show your Heads, if the Highest give forth His Voice with Hail-stones and Coals of Fire.</hi> Methinks there is that Song of <hi>Hannah</hi> in the <hi>Thunder,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.3, 10. <hi>Talk no more so Exceeding proudly, Let not Arrogancy come out of your Mouth. For the Adversaries of the Lord shall be broken to pieces, out of Heaven shall He Thunder upon them.</hi> The Omnipotent God in the <hi>Thunder</hi> speaks to those hardy <hi>Typhons,</hi> that are found <hi>Fighting</hi> against Him; and says, <hi>Oh! do not harden your selves against such a God; You are not Stronger than He!</hi> Yea, the Great God is proposed as an Object for our <hi>Faith,</hi> as well as for our <hi>Fear</hi> in his <hi>Thunder.</hi> If Nothing be <hi>too hard</hi> for the <hi>Thunder,</hi> we may
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171426:8"/>
               <hi>of my Salvation, and I have waited for Him!</hi> I say, let the <hi>Thunders</hi> drive you on to this Attainment.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. A Fourth <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorious God</hi> in the <hi>Thunder,</hi> is, <hi>Make your Peace with God immediately, lest by the Stroke of his Thunder he take you away in His Wrath.</hi> Why is it that Persons are usually in such a Consternation at the <hi>Thunder?</hi> Indeed there is a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexional</hi> and <hi>Constitutional</hi> weakness in many this way; they have such a Disadvantage in a <hi>Frightful temper,</hi> that no Considerations can wholly overcome it. But most usualy the <hi>Frights</hi> of People at the <hi>Thunder,</hi> arise from the <hi>Terms</hi> wherein they may suspect their own Souls to stand before an <hi>Angry God.</hi> Their <hi>Consciences</hi> tell them that their <hi>Sins</hi> are yet unpardoned, that their <hi>Hearts</hi> are yet unrenewed, that their <hi>Title</hi> to Blessedness is yet unsettled, and that if the next <hi>Thunder-clap</hi> shoud strike them Dead, it had been good for them that they had never been Born.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hi sunt qui trepidant, &amp; ad omnia Fulgura pallent;</l>
               <l>Cum tonat, Exanimes primo quo{que} murmure Coeli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Here then is the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in the <hi>Thunder, Art thou Ready? Soul, Art thou Ready? make Ready present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lest I call for thee before thou art aware.</hi> There is in a <hi>Thunder</hi> a vehement Call unto that <hi>Regeneration,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Repenting of <hi>Sin,</hi> that Believing on <hi>Christ;</hi> and that Consenting unto the Demands of the <hi>New-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> without which no man in his Wits can Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably hold up his Face before the <hi>Thunder.</hi> I have now in my House a Marriners <hi>Compass,</hi> whereupon a <hi>Thunder-clap</hi> had this odd Effect, that the <hi>North-point</hi> was thereby <hi>turned</hi> clear about unto the <hi>South,</hi> and so it will veer and stand ever since unto this day, tho' the thing happened above thirteen years ago.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171426:9"/>I would to God that the next <hi>Thunder-claps</hi> would give as effectual a <hi>turn</hi> unto all the unconverted Souls among us! May the <hi>Thunder</hi> awaken you to <hi>turn</hi> from every Vanity to God in Christ without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, lest by the <hi>Thunder</hi> it self it come quickly to be too late. It is a <hi>vulgar Error,</hi> that the <hi>Thunder</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kills any who are <hi>asleep:</hi> Man, what if the <hi>Thunder</hi> should kill thee in the <hi>dead sleep</hi> of thy <hi>Ʋnregeneracy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A fifth <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorious God</hi> in the <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> is, <hi>Let this Thunder convict you of what you may justly reckon your own iniquity.</hi> Every Man has his own peculiar <hi>Sin,</hi> a <hi>Sin</hi> whereby the Soul of the Man is more exposed and endangered, than by any other sin; his <hi>Darling-sin,</hi> his <hi>Master-sin,</hi> or that which bids fairest so to be. <hi>David</hi> being delivered from Damage by the <hi>Thunder,</hi> ascribes it unto the favour of God [2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.24.] Rewarding him for <hi>keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself from his own iniquity.</hi> This I say the <hi>Thunder</hi> may do us the favour of informing us, what is <hi>our own iniquity,</hi> and that would be a Favour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed! There are some sort of <hi>Writings</hi> which you can't read until you hold them against the <hi>Fire;</hi> would you read the worst Guiltiness and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of your own Hearts? Then say I, <hi>hold them up against the Lightning,</hi> my meaning is this; when it <hi>Thunders,</hi> do you observe about what Miscarriage your Hearts do first and most of all <hi>then</hi> misgive you; observe which of all your Faults <hi>then</hi> do's <hi>first</hi> of all, and <hi>most</hi> of all, stare you in the face, with formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Criminations. You may now take it for granted, this is <hi>your own iniquity.</hi> And the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is, <hi>do you keep a special Watch against that iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and against all the Beginnings, all the Occasions, all the Incentives of that Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. A sixth <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorious God</hi> in the <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171426:9"/>is, <hi>Take heed now, take heed ever, of those grosser sins, which have sometimes been revenged by Thunder.</hi> There have been the ireful and the direful <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of God, sometimes used for the Executions of his Vengeance upon such and such Enormities: The perpetual Admonitions of the <hi>Thunders</hi> are, <hi>take heed of such Thunder-struck Abominations.</hi> As now, the Cities now buried, (tho' they say of late by the sinking of the Water growing visible again) in the Lake of <hi>Sodom. Tacitus</hi> the Roman Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian truely tells us, they perished <hi>Fulminum jactu,</hi> by <hi>Thunder-bolts;</hi> God sent an extraordinary <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-storm</hi> upon them, for the <hi>Lusts of Ʋncleanness,</hi> wherein they <hi>burned.</hi> Wherefore, when it <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in it, is, <hi>put out the unclean fires of Lust in your Souls, lest I set you on fire, by my dreadful Thunders!</hi> Again, there was <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> who offered <hi>strange fire</hi> to God, and God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them with a killing <hi>fire</hi> from Heaven, in a hideous <hi>Thunder-storm;</hi> so then, when it <hi>Thunders,</hi> the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in it, is, <hi>Look well to all your sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, lest my fire make you a sacrifice, see that you duely attend my Worship, lest my Thunder fall upon you!</hi> Once more; there was <hi>Ʋzzah</hi> who fell into an <hi>Error,</hi> in his management about the <hi>Ark</hi> of God; and it seems as if a <hi>Thunder-storm</hi> suddenly coming up, kill'd him for it. Hence then, when it <hi>Thunders,</hi> the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in it, is, <hi>Look to it, that my Ark, and my Word, find no contempt with you, lest my Thunder chastise you for your contempt.</hi> What shall I say more? <hi>Corah</hi> was destroyed by <hi>Thunder</hi> for his <hi>Rebellion</hi> against God and <hi>Moses,</hi> wherefore the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Thunder,</hi> is, <hi>Take heed of all Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against God and Jesus.</hi> The <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines,</hi> the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> were confounded with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solating
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171426:10"/>
               <hi>Thunders,</hi> because they invaded and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the People of God. It is then the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Thunder, see that you do no wrong unto an holy people, that have this Artillery of Heaven to defend them.</hi> They that are <hi>such Witnesses</hi> for God and Reformation as <hi>Elijah</hi> was, have, as he had, the <hi>Fires</hi> of <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> to <hi>devour those that hurt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. A Seventh <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Glorious God</hi> in the <hi>Thunder,</hi> is, <hi>Hear the voice of my Word, lest I make you fear the voice of my Thunder.</hi> When the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Egypt</hi> persisted in their Disobedience to the <hi>Word</hi> of God, it came to that at last, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.23. <hi>The Lord sent Thunder, and the fire ran along upon the Ground.</hi> Thus the Eternal God commands Men to <hi>let</hi> go their sins, and <hi>go</hi> themselves to <hi>serve</hi> him; if they are disobedient, they lay themselves open to <hi>fiery Thunders.</hi> This you may be sure is the <hi>Voice</hi> of God in the <hi>Thunder, Hear my still voice in my Ordinances, lest you put me upon speaking to you with more angry Thunderbolts.</hi> I have known it sometimes remark'd, that very Notorious and Resolved <hi>Sleepers</hi> at <hi>Sermons,</hi> often have some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <hi>suddenness</hi> in the Circumstances of their <hi>Death.</hi> Truly, if you are scandalously given to <hi>sleep</hi> under the Word of God, and much more if to <hi>sin</hi> under it, and most of all, if to <hi>scoff</hi> under it, it may be your Deaths will be rendred <hi>sudden</hi> by the other <hi>Thunders</hi> of Heaven lighting on you. When it <hi>thunders,</hi> God saith to all the Hearers of his Word ordinarily preached, <hi>Consider this, and forget not God, lest he tear you to pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, And is there not this <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God</hi> in the <hi>Thunder</hi> after all? <hi>Oh be thankful to the gracious God, that the thunder does no more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:171426:10"/>
            <p>Whatever the <hi>Witch-advocates</hi> may make of it, it is a Scriptural and a Rational Assertion, <hi>that in the Thunder there is oftentimes, by the permission of God, the Agency of the Devil.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> is the <hi>Prince of the power of the Air,</hi> and when God gives him leave, he has a vast <hi>power in the Air,</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> that can <hi>make thunders in the Air.</hi> We are certain that <hi>Satan</hi> had his Efficiency in it, when the <hi>Fire of God,</hi> or the <hi>Lightning,</hi> fell upon part of <hi>Job's</hi> Estate, how glad would he have been, if the good Man himself had been in the way to have been torn in pieces, and perhaps it was the Hellish Policy of the Wicked One, thus to make the good Man suspicious that God was become his Enemy. <hi>Popes</hi> that have been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers, have made <hi>fire</hi> thus <hi>come from Heaven,</hi> by their Confederacies with <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> and we have in our own Land known <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> plainly disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering their Concurrence in Disasters thus occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. A great Man has therefore noted it, <hi>that Thunders break oftner on Churches than any other Houses,</hi> because the <hi>Daemons</hi> have a peculiar spite at Houses that are set apart for the peculiar Service of God. I say then, live we thus in the midst of <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and of <hi>Devils</hi> too; and yet live we? Oh! Let us be thankful to the God of our <hi>Lives,</hi> are we not smitten by the <hi>great Ordnance of Heaven,</hi> discharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever now and then on every side of us? Let us be thankful to the great Lord of Heaven, who makes even <hi>the Wrath of Hell to praise him, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of that Wrath does he restrain.</hi> Such a Serious <hi>Thankfulness</hi> manifested in an Answerable <hi>Fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> will be still continually a better shelter to us from the Mischefs of the <hi>Thunder,</hi> than the Crowns of <hi>Laurel,</hi> or the Tents of <hi>Seal-Leather</hi> whereby some Old Emperours counted themselves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171426:11"/>protected; or than all their <hi>Amulets</hi> of Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>To the Custody of <hi>Israel</hi>'s Great <hi>Keeper</hi> I now commend you all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:171426:11"/>
            <head>THE VOICE of THUNDERS, Heard <hi>September</hi> 16. 1694.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>It is written REV. VIII. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— And there were Voices, and Thundrings, and Lightnings, and an Earthquake.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>§. THere were two Famous <hi>Ministers</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, upon whom our Lord in his <hi>New Creation</hi> did put very signal <hi>Names,</hi> as was done of Old unto some significanter and considerabler parts of the <hi>Old Creation,</hi> because they were to bear a more than common Figure in this <hi>New Creation,</hi> and as it is said <hi>Mark</hi> 3.17. <hi>He surnamed them Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerges, which is, the sons of Thunder.</hi> The Word for <hi>Thunder,</hi> in that Name signifieth <hi>Earthquake</hi> as well as <hi>Thunder:</hi> And Learned Men think, that our Lord in giving that Name to these Eminent Men, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect unto that Prophecy in <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I will shake all Nations, and the desire of all Nations shall come.</hi> It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry possible, that these two Ministers of our Lord had, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> intimateth, a lively, notable, audible delivery, in their Preaching, by the advantage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Truths of God by them delivered, came like so many Soul-surprising <hi>Thunders</hi> upon the Souls of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171426:12"/>those that were the Hearers. But this is not all, there were mighty <hi>Commotions</hi> in subserviency unto the Interests of the Gospel, then to be effected, and our Lord would have a singular Improvement made of these two Ministers, for the producing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of those <hi>Commotions;</hi> and in the midst of those <hi>Revolutions</hi> these two Ambassadors of the Lord were to carry the Gospel with a force like that of <hi>Thunder,</hi> thro' the Jewish Nation: For this cause were <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> called <hi>the Sons of Thunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. Indeed our Lord expects this from all his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, that they should endeavour to be <hi>Boanerges</hi>'s, in the dispensations of his Word unto <hi>every Creature</hi> under the <hi>Firmament</hi> thereof: But, O how much may I think, that the Lord, <hi>whose I am, and whom I serve,</hi> does expect such an Endeavour of sinful <hi>me,</hi> who have been newly signalized by the merciful and marvellous Thunders of the Lord. When <hi>Moses,</hi> the <hi>Servant of the Lord,</hi> had been in the midst of those terrible Thunders, which were on every side of him, tearing all before them, he went from thence down unto his Congregation, with the <hi>Laws</hi> of God in his hand. <hi>My Brethren,</hi> I must come unto you this day with those <hi>holy, and just, and good Laws</hi> of God, wherein you are are now to be sensible of louder Thunders then those, from the midst which it is that I am come. In-as-much as the <hi>Thunders</hi> of God have lately been falling on my House, I suppose and believe it is his will, that I should now be filling of <hi>his house</hi> with the greater <hi>Thunders</hi> of his Word. It is the Remark of the Scripture on the <hi>Thunder,</hi> that the <hi>Rain</hi> accompanieth it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.13. 'tis said, <hi>When he uttereth his voice, there is a multitude of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Heavens, and he causeth the vapours to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend from the ends of the Earth, he maketh lightning with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171426:12"/>rain, and bringeth forth the Wind out of his treasures:</hi> Yea, but the <hi>Word</hi> of God, which <hi>cleanses</hi> and <hi>soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens</hi> the Hearts of Men, is on many accounts compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the <hi>Rain,</hi> the Doctrines of that Word are to <hi>fall as Rain upon the Grass. Christians,</hi> the <hi>Rain</hi> of God is this Afternoon to fall among you; but, O let this <hi>Rain</hi> sink deep into every one of your Hearts, and the deeper, because of the concomitant <hi>Thunders,</hi> that give an <hi>Accent</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>§. I am carrying of you into that <hi>Revelation,</hi> which is the <hi>last Letter</hi> that we have had from the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ in Heaven, for these by-past sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years; the <hi>Scope</hi> of which <hi>Letter</hi> is to advertise us, how our Lord having begun to set up his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World, by the preaching of the Gospel, would <hi>overturn, overturn, overturn,</hi> and from time to time, confound all powers that make head against it, until the <hi>coming</hi> of him, who doth here say, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I come quickly.</hi> It is a <hi>Commentary</hi> on what hath been written by <hi>Daniel,</hi> on the <hi>Fourth Monarchy,</hi> with some Touches upon that approaching <hi>Fifth;</hi> wherein <hi>the Kingdom shall be the Lords, and the Lord shall be Governour among the Nations; wherein the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Dominion, and the Greatness of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom under the whole Heaven, shall be given to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Saints of the most High;</hi> and wherein there shall be a <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> in which there <hi>shall dwell Righteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. There was a <hi>Volume,</hi> a Volume of divers leaves, inscribed both on the <hi>backside</hi> and <hi>inside,</hi> and rolled into a <hi>Cylindriacal</hi> form, under seven <hi>Labels,</hi> fasten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with so many seals; the <hi>showing</hi> and <hi>opening</hi> of this <hi>Volume</hi> unto the <hi>Beloved Disciple,</hi> gave unto him a Scheme of what was to come to pass, from the <hi>Ascension</hi> to the <hi>second coming</hi> of our Lord. The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171426:13"/>Book being unrolled and unfolded, there were <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Trumpets,</hi> with many wonderful Circumstances, exposed unto the view of this <hi>Disciple;</hi> which <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets</hi> are to denote seven most memorable Judgments of God upon the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> to make way for the Kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ. These Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are most sitly exhibited under the Notion of so many <hi>Trumpets,</hi> all sounding as the <hi>Cornets</hi> for <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days</hi> about <hi>Jericho</hi> of Old, for the fall of it; so these for the fall of the <hi>Romish Jericho;</hi> in as-much as they sound the Allarums of Divine Vengeance against the World, for their Indisposition unto the Reign of our Lord.</p>
            <p>§. <hi>John</hi> was prepared for that sight of these Judgments in the seven <hi>Trumpets,</hi> by an amazing Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a most Heavenly and Glorious Matter, in the eternal Temple of God. If you will now walk with me, I will carry you unto that Coelestial <hi>Temple,</hi> and you shall see those things, which <hi>blessed are your eyes that they may see such things this day!</hi> In the <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi> it was the usage of the High-Priest that he should there cause <hi>Incense</hi> to <hi>ascend</hi> before the Lord, from the <hi>Golden Altar</hi> of Incense. This is done, this very thing is done continually by the Lord Jesus Christ, who <hi>ever lives, that he may be doing so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi> For that cause we are here told, <hi>An Angel came and stood at the Altar, having a Golden Censor, and there was given unto him much Incense, that he should offer it with the prayers of all Saints upon the Golden Altar, which was before the Throne: And the smoak of the Incense, which came with the prayers of the Saints, ascended up before God, out of the Angels hand.</hi> Our Lord Jesus Christ is that <hi>Angel of the Lord,</hi> even the <hi>Angel</hi> who is the <hi>Lord of Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Angel the Lord.</hi> Our <hi>Prayers,</hi> as far as the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171426:13"/>is in the Composition of them, are grateful to the Lord Jesus Christ; we bring our allowable Desires to that praying Lord, and he takes them into his illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious Hand, he <hi>perfumes</hi> them, he <hi>offers</hi> them, he causes them to go up like the Odour of sweet <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense</hi> before his everlasting Father; yea, if there be any <hi>fleshly</hi> savour in the Sacrifices of our Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that odious and loathsome <hi>Nidour</hi> is taken away by this <hi>Incense</hi> of our Lord.</p>
            <p>§. In our Text we have the effect of <hi>Supplication</hi> to the Lord, made effectual by the <hi>Intercessions</hi> of the Lord; <hi>the Angel takes the Censor, and filleth it with fire of the Altar, and casteth it into the Earth,</hi> to make way for those Effects. But now the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> of the Prayers that are made by the pious, what are these? <hi>they were Voices, and Thundrings, and Lightnings, and an Earthquake.</hi> And what was the meaning of these things? Perhaps here may be an <hi>Hendiades,</hi> by <hi>voices,</hi> and <hi>thundrings,</hi> and <hi>lightnings,</hi> may be meant the voices of <hi>thunderings</hi> and <hi>lightnings:</hi> No <hi>wonder</hi> that an <hi>Earthquake</hi> is added hereunto, for <hi>thundrings</hi> and <hi>lightnings</hi> do pretty often go with <hi>earthquakes;</hi> they did so when <hi>Corah</hi> perished, and they are so denounced in <hi>Isa.</hi> 29.6. <hi>Thou shalt be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited of the Lord of hosts with thunder, and with earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and great noise, with storm and tempest, and the flame of devouring fire.</hi> But the signification of these <hi>Appearances</hi> in our Text was thus much: It was not only that God had <hi>Plagues</hi> in Store for his Enemies, but also that the <hi>Prayers</hi> of his People found Acceptance with him.</p>
            <p>§. Agreeably unto this, you shall have these things more particularly remarked unto you in <hi>three Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi> with their <hi>Applications,</hi> to be made upon these words of the Lord among you.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:171426:14"/>
            <p>§ The first <hi>Reflection</hi> is, <hi>The most faithful God of Heaven, who sometimes hath loudly testified by Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings and Lightnings, that he hath heard the Prayers of his faithful People, hath indeed his Ear always open to their faithful prayers.</hi> The Saints have their <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> ascending before God; these <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Saints are accepted with God: How is this discover'd? by <hi>Thundrings and Lightnings</hi> that come thereupon, wherein God as it were says concerning them, <hi>Your prayers are come up, your prayers have pierced the clouds that are now breaking over you.</hi> This <hi>Reflection</hi> is to be pursued with two <hi>Observations</hi> and one <hi>Inference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. The first <hi>Observation</hi> is, <hi>Great Thunders have been sometimes given as a testimony that the prayers of good men have been heard by the great God of those Thunders.</hi> It is here said, <hi>there were Voices, and Thundrings, and Lightnings.</hi> What were the <hi>Voices</hi> therein contained? The <hi>Voices</hi> were, <hi>Your Prayers, Your Prayers are come up before God;</hi> God will tell you thus with replies Louder than those of the loudest <hi>Thunders</hi> were. The Clouds of sincere and speeding <hi>Prayers,</hi> have more then once before now shot <hi>fiery Thunderbolts.</hi> It is what we have exemplified in <hi>Psal.</hi> 18.6. <hi>In my distress I called upon the Lord, and cried unto my God; he heard my voice out of his Temple, and my cry came before him, even into his Ears.</hi> And what then? As a sign of this, <hi>the Lord thundered in the Heavens, and the Highest gave forth his voice; Hail stones and coals of fire, yea, he sent out his arrows, and he shot out his Lightnings.</hi> When our Lord Jesus Christ had been crying to his everlasting Father, that by his means much Glory and service might come to the Name of such a <hi>Father,</hi> there was then a <hi>voice</hi> from Heaven, heard over the place where he stood, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.28. whereupon the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171426:14"/>People that stood by and heard it, <hi>said, that it thundered; others said, an Angel spake to him, but Jesus answered and said, this voice came not because of me, but for your sakes. Samuel,</hi> that reverend and renowned Prophet of the Lord, had been <hi>calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord,</hi> for an evidence of his being what he <hi>was,</hi> and strait-way there was that <hi>Evidence</hi> of it, record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1 Sam. 12.18. <hi>Samuel called unto the Lord, and the Lord sent thunder: and rain, and all the People, greatly feared.</hi> It is a most memorable passage, which is, in <hi>Psal.</hi> 81.7. <hi>I answered thee in the secret place of thunder.</hi> A Critical Interpreter has this Gloss upon it, <hi>tu invocasti me in secreto Ego exaudivi te manifeste, publico tonitrui miraculo: My publick thunders</hi> answer thy <hi>secret Prayers. Moses</hi> had been much in Prayer with and for <hi>Israel;</hi> God heard his Prayer; and how did he prove that? <hi>from the secret place of thunder.</hi> What says the Psalmist, in <hi>Psal.</hi> 65.5, 8. <hi>By terrible things in righteousness wilt thou answer us, O God of our Salvation.</hi> How will he answer? <hi>they that dwell in the uttermost parts are afraid at thy tokens,</hi> i.e. <hi>thy thunders;</hi> which are thy <hi>tokens terrible,</hi> and yet <hi>Comfortable,</hi> yet <hi>Favourable.</hi> The <hi>thunders</hi> of God have sometimes been the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of <hi>Prayers</hi> that have been sent up to God, —</p>
            <p>§. But then our next <hi>Observation</hi> is, <hi>tho' such extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary tokens of prevailing Prayers, as thunders, are not now to be expected, yet the prevalency of good men's Prayers is always to be believed, as much as if the shrill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thunders had assured it.</hi> There are <hi>voices</hi> equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sonorous unto those of the <hi>thunderings</hi> and <hi>lightnings;</hi> and what are they? They are such as those in <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me, and I will deliver thee, and thou shalt Glorifie me.</hi> What is the Name of God? it is <hi>the Hearer of Prayer;</hi> he will sooner
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171426:15"/>forget his <hi>Name,</hi> then leave of to be so. <hi>Both Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> do speak this unto us, as with concurring <hi>thunders.</hi> From the Old Testament you hear it spoken in Psal. 34.15. <hi>The Ear of the Lord is open to the Cry of the Righteous.</hi> You hear it spoken from the New Testament in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>If we ask any thing according to his Will, he heareth us.</hi> The Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of a right Prayer are, <hi>Cum boni petant bonum benè &amp; ad bonum;</hi> when <hi>good men</hi> do ask a <hi>good God,</hi> for <hi>good things,</hi> after a <hi>good manner,</hi> and unto a <hi>good purpose.</hi> Now I am to tell you, that <hi>such prayers are never lost,</hi> there is an Assurace from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven given us, beyond that of <hi>thunder</hi> from the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Glory,</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 91.15. <hi>He shall call upon me, and I will answer him.</hi> Who is this that shall thus call upon God, and God will answer him? <hi>He that hath set his love upon me, and hath known my name.</hi> This was ever the experience of all those that seared God. For the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of this Assurance, there are two things that are said unto us: One is, <hi>every one that is godly will pray;</hi> and another is, <hi>this poor man cryed, and the Lord heard.</hi> Let us be much in <hi>Prayer</hi> to God, by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God; and therefore let our <hi>prayer</hi> to God be much for that <hi>Spirit,</hi> so let us <hi>pray without ceasing,</hi> and you shall make then such a conclusion with me as this, <hi>Psal.</hi> 6.9. <hi>The Lord hath heard the voice of my weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> of God gives unto a Servant of God, a strong, and a firm, and full Perswasion, that his <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> are heard; he does it more signally than if the <hi>thunders</hi> themselves were to utter it, — Well then, the <hi>Inference</hi> to be raised from hence, is,</p>
            <p>§. <hi>That those who are fervent in Prayers, need not be afraid of thunders:</hi> There is a <hi>filial fear</hi> of God in the <hi>thunders,</hi> which well becomes a <hi>Child</hi> of God, a reverend, a serious and sensible Disposition of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171426:15"/>Soul. He was a <hi>Child</hi> of God, who when it was <hi>thundring,</hi> (as is conceived) said, <hi>Job</hi> 37.1. <hi>At this my heart trembled!</hi> But then there is a <hi>slavish fear</hi> of the <hi>thunder,</hi> which is offensive unto the <hi>God of thunder,</hi> and which is troublesome and afflictive enough to those that have the fear. It was said when it <hi>thundred,</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 46.6. <hi>He uttered his voice, the Earth melted:</hi> Even so it may be said of many; <hi>when God uttered his voice, their heart is melted;</hi> but I say, a <hi>Praying Man</hi> may be above such a <hi>carnal,</hi> and such a shaking, and such a sinful fear. What tho' the <hi>thunder</hi> should kill such a man, as it <hi>may</hi> do, and <hi>has</hi> done, yet still it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do the man any <hi>hurt;</hi> it may kill him, but it will only send him perhaps the <hi>easiest way to Heaven</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was gone: Besides, let a man be abundant in <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and such a man may say, <hi>I serve such a God that will never hurt me, he is concerned for my Peace, he is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for my ease, and he is concerned for my universal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</hi> They that are much in <hi>speaking to God,</hi> need not have their hearts to fail them, when they hear <hi>God speaking</hi> to them; instead of <hi>that,</hi> were you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent when such a man is entertained with the <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> you should hear him saying, <hi>It is my Fathers voice, we must not be afraid!</hi> As for those that are so much <hi>afraid,</hi> as even to loose themselves and their wits, when God is <hi>thundring</hi> over them, shall we invert those words that are in <hi>Job</hi> 15.4. <hi>Thou castest off fear, and restrainest prayer before God?</hi> and say, therefore it is that they are in <hi>such fear,</hi> because they <hi>restrain Prayers before God?</hi> Oh! that the <hi>thunder</hi> of God might then bespeak our <hi>seasonable Prayers</hi> unto him; our Prayers, I say, before we may justly imagine he is going to cut us off by the Thunder-bolts of his Indignation; what a lamentable case is it when a poor Creature is under the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171426:16"/>for him <hi>then</hi> to say, <hi>there is a God whom I am not yet at peace withall! I have never yet prayed aright unto that God whose thunders now drive me to my Prayers!</hi> They that are strangers to Prayer, with what face can they look to God, when he shoots down <hi>thundring</hi> and <hi>lightning</hi> upon them? God says then to them, <hi>Do you pray now, you should have prayed before this!</hi> Oh! consider of it, this is our first <hi>Reflection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶. But now the second <hi>Reflection</hi> is, <hi>in answer to the Prayers of his faithful people, the God of Heaven will cause those Earthquakes that shall shake terribly the earth, and even shake the Earth to pieces.</hi> When there were <hi>thundrings</hi> and <hi>lightnings</hi> upon the <hi>voices</hi> of the Saints, (we'll say) in their <hi>Prayers,</hi> there was an <hi>Earthquake</hi> too. What litterally came to pass in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25, 26. <hi>At midnight Paul and Silas prayed, and sang praises unto God, and suddenly there was a great earthquake;</hi> that <hi>figuratively</hi> and <hi>meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically</hi> much oftner comes to pass, when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are praying to him he makes prodigious <hi>Earth-quakes</hi> for them, <hi>State-quakes,</hi> and <hi>Nation-quakes,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom-quakes</hi> are caused by the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the faithful People of God. There were two such pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Isaiah,</hi> who were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Church; when they <hi>prayed,</hi> this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Psal.</hi> 64.3. [I suppose the Psalm written by one of them] <hi>The Earth removed, the Water swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the Mountains shook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are Three <hi>Meditations,</hi> which are to adjust this <hi>Reflection,</hi> and from them one <hi>Corollary</hi> is to be deduced.</p>
            <p>§. The first <hi>Meditation</hi> is, <hi>They are usually cruel and bloody persecutions upon the people of God, which drive them to their prayers: Now the Persecutions of a praying people bring shaking desolations upon the Persecutors.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171426:16"/>The Oppressors of the Church do that thing in <hi>Job.</hi> 34.28. <hi>They cause the cry of the poor to come unto God, and he heareth the cry of the afflicted.</hi> What comes of this? why, horrible overturning <hi>Earthquake,</hi> have come upon all those <hi>Empires,</hi> wherein there has been an oppressed people of God? The <hi>Cup of tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> in <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> has been carried unto all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms hitherto where the People of God have been evilly treated; Why so? Because that People have been driven to more then ordinary <hi>Praying,</hi> by the Persecution of their Adversaries. Hence we read concerning the <hi>Praying Witnesses,</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. <hi>their Enemies beheld them, and the same hour there was a great Earthquake;</hi> that very <hi>Earthquake,</hi> which you may Believe it, <hi>Aeurope</hi> is now entered into. The <hi>Earth,</hi> from whence there has gon a cry to the <hi>Lord God of Sabaoth,</hi> for the violence done to his People, shall be shaken with an <hi>Earthquake;</hi> Why this? it is thro' the Praying of the <hi>Witnesses;</hi> they <hi>Cry</hi> to God from the <hi>Earth,</hi> and God shaketh that <hi>Earth,</hi> upon which they have been abused.</p>
            <p>§. The Second <hi>Meditation</hi> is, <hi>the Anger of God is dreadfully burning against those that inflame the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his People, and that anger will make stupendous Earthquakes of them.</hi> The Omnipotent God is angry at them, who cause the <hi>Complaints</hi> of those that are <hi>grieved, when they behold transgressors,</hi> who cause the Complaints of those that <hi>Sigh and cry for the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that are done where they are;</hi> and who cause the Complaints of those whose <hi>righteous Souls are vexed by their ungodly deeds.</hi> But what will the Issue of that <hi>Anger</hi> be? An <hi>Earthquake</hi> will be the Issue of it. It was said <hi>Job.</hi> 9.5.6. <hi>He removeth the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and they know not: He overturneth them in his Anger: He shaketh the Earth out of her place, the pillars
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171426:17"/>thereof tremble.</hi> And it was said, <hi>Isa.</hi> 13.13. <hi>I will shake the Heavens, and the Earth shall remove out of her place, in the wrath of the Lord of Hosts, and in the day of his fierce Anger.</hi> Even so, when the <hi>Anger</hi> of God comes upon those about them, against whom his People has been Complaining, that <hi>Anger</hi> will tumble all into confusion; it shall be notorious, that there is no standing before an <hi>Angry</hi> God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will make the very <hi>Earth to reel like a drunken Man,</hi> as it is said <hi>Isa.</hi> 24.18, 19. <hi>The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Earth do shake, the earth is utterly broken down, the earth is clean dissolved, the earth is moved exceedingly; the earth shall reel too and fro like a drunkard, and shall be removed like a Cottage, and the transgression thereof shall be heavy upon it, and it shall fall, and not rise again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. The third <hi>Meditation</hi> is, <hi>The Kingdom of God is to come, according to the Prayers of his People, but without most horrendous Earthquakes that Kingdom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come.</hi> When <hi>Israel</hi> went out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> there seems to have been an <hi>Earthquake,</hi> which contribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the parting of the Sea; for tho' <hi>Moses</hi> writ nothing of it in <hi>Exodus,</hi> yet <hi>he</hi> or some other does in <hi>Psal.</hi> 77.18, 19. <hi>The voice of thy Thunder was in the Heaven; the Lightnings lightned the World, the Earth trembled and shook: Thy way is in the Sea, and thy path in the great Witers, and thy foot-steps are not known:</hi> An <hi>Earthquake</hi> made a <hi>path</hi> for them thorow the <hi>Waters.</hi> Even so the <hi>Waters</hi> are to be divided at this day, that so the <hi>Israel</hi> of God may have such a passage to his Worship as they are to have. Again, the Romish <hi>Corah</hi> that stands up against the Lord Jesus Christ must be extinguished: How? It was an <hi>Earthquake</hi> that swallowed the Crew which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Corah;</hi> so God will make an <hi>Earthquake</hi> that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171426:17"/>shall swallow the <hi>Corahites</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Once more, when the last <hi>Hour-glass</hi> of the Papacy is running, <hi>Then there will be voices, and Thunderings, and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and a great Earthquake, such as was not since Men were upon the Earth.</hi> As at the <hi>Resurrection</hi> of our Lord there was an <hi>Earthquake,</hi> for the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Stone</hi> that kept him in the Grave, so upon the <hi>Prayers</hi> of his People for the removing of those <hi>disadvantages</hi> that keep them under hatches, there will be an <hi>Earthquake.</hi> There are those <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies</hi> and <hi>Contrarieties</hi> in the hearts of mankind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Interests of the Lord Jesus Christ, that must be <hi>shaken</hi> out, that so men may be prepared for the coming of the Lord; but they will not without horrible <hi>Earthquakes</hi> be shaken out. Hence our Lord says, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26. <hi>Yet once more I shake not the Earth only, but also Heaven;</hi> Why so? to make way for those things that <hi>cannot be shaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Corollary</hi> is this: <hi>Hence in our days the most astonishing Earthquakes that ever shook the World, are now like to shake it.</hi> From the <hi>Altar</hi> there comes an <hi>Earthquake:</hi> There have been <hi>Souls under the Altar</hi> for these <hi>many ages,</hi> and the number of the Souls is increased and compleated in this our <hi>latter age.</hi> Hence now may be expected a <hi>great Earthquake,</hi> that shall make all to fly before it. <hi>Proper Earthquakes</hi> are now like to be multiplied, Our Lord has given us the premonition in <hi>Luke.</hi> 21.11. <hi>and great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes shall be in divers places.</hi> The <hi>Subterranious fires</hi> that are to burn e're long, will get head, so that on a sudden a great <hi>Earthquake</hi> will be pusht on by these <hi>Fires.</hi> Yea, there is one Earthquake to come, and a <hi>Proper</hi> one, wherein Millions of Men shall Perish: <hi>Italy</hi> shall know when <hi>that</hi> cometh. Be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> I say then, Be ready for them.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171426:18"/>What if the Earth should now set a shaking under us? Are we sure that we shall not <hi>Go up,</hi> when ever we <hi>Go down?</hi> The Earth will <hi>Open</hi> for us all in a little while, the <hi>Sexton</hi> will <hi>Open</hi> it, when we shall be carried on the arms of our friends into it: And God knows whether His own Hand may not <hi>Open</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> more wonderfully and suddenly, for those that are little aware of it! But however, <hi>Improper Earthquakes</hi> will come on amain; It was said in the <hi>Psalm</hi> inspired into <hi>Deborah, Judg.</hi> 5.4, 5. <hi>Lord, when thou wentest out of</hi> Seir, <hi>when thou march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edst out of the Field of</hi> Edom, <hi>the Earth trembled, and the Heavens dropped, and the Clouds also dropped Water, the Mountains melted from before the Lord.</hi> Sirs, the Lord is coming forth from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and think you not that the <hi>Earth</hi> will <hi>shake</hi> when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? There are dreadful <hi>Convulsions</hi> that will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon the World; <hi>Convulsions</hi> that shall overset both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Sacred</hi> Orders; <hi>Convulsions</hi> that shall sheath the <hi>Swords</hi> of Men into one anothers <hi>Bowels; Convulsions</hi> that shall make mens <hi>hearts to fail, for fear of those things that come upon the Earth!</hi> But so much for the second <hi>Reflection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ The third and last <hi>Reflection</hi> is, When the Almighty God sends <hi>Thunderings</hi> and <hi>Lightnings,</hi> as well as when he sends <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> there are <hi>Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Voices</hi> to accompany them. <hi>Voices</hi> here go with the <hi>Thundering</hi> and <hi>Lightnings</hi> and <hi>Earthquakes.</hi> The <hi>Earthquakes</hi> have their Voices; there is a <hi>Speaking</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> in the tremend <hi>shaking</hi> of the Earth, but <hi>Thunderings</hi> and <hi>Lightnings</hi> are the things, the <hi>Voices</hi> whereof do now most call for our attention. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, This Reflection shall be conveyed into your minds, with only a double <hi>Admonition,</hi> and so we shall conclude.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171426:18"/>
            <p>§. The first <hi>Admonition</hi> is, <hi>Natural Thunders have a Mighty Voice of the Almighty God in them, and it is our Duty to hear that Voice.</hi> The <hi>Thunders</hi> 'tis most Emphatically called, <hi>the Voice of God;</hi> so <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> so <hi>Elihu</hi> called it. Indeed there are <hi>Natural</hi> Causes for Thunders, but still these <hi>Causes,</hi> as well as the <hi>Thunders</hi> caused, are under the Conduct of God, the <hi>High Thunderer.</hi> If a <hi>Bird</hi> fall not, I am sure a <hi>Bolt</hi> falls not without His will. The <hi>Angels</hi> are often times employed in the forming of his <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Good <hi>Angels</hi> and Bad <hi>Angels</hi> too, are the <hi>Thunderers;</hi> but still the Executioners of God's <hi>Thunder,</hi> and under God's Commission. It is said, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.24. <hi>that there was the noise of the living Creatures in their wings, like the noise of great Waters, as the voice of the Almighty:</hi> i. e. As the Thunders, these <hi>living Creatures,</hi> there are their <hi>voices</hi> in the <hi>Thunders</hi> oft, but it is <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>with,</hi> and <hi>under</hi> the <hi>voice of the Almighty:</hi> So then the <hi>voice</hi> hereof is to be attended unto. Will you be <hi>deaf to Thunder,</hi> Hear the <hi>Voice of God,</hi> when he <hi>Thunders,</hi> as he has lately done; first, the <hi>voice</hi> of the Almighty in the <hi>Thunder,</hi> is, <hi>Adore the power of God, and Fear such a God.</hi> It was said in <hi>Psal.</hi> 76.7, 8. <hi>Who may stand in thy sight, when once thou art angry? Thou didst cause judgment,</hi> i. e. Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>to be heard from Heaven, the Earth feared and was still.</hi> It is elsewhere said, <hi>That the strength of God is in the Clouds:</hi> The <hi>Thunder</hi> in the Clouds does proclaim the <hi>Strength</hi> of God. It is also said, <hi>Hast thou an Arm like God? Or canst thou Thunder with a Voice like Him?</hi> The <hi>Thunder</hi> tells us what an Arm he hath. This then is the <hi>Voice</hi> of Thunder, <hi>O who dares lay himself open to the displeasure of this God, that can by Thunders strike him into a Piller of Salt!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. Secondly, The <hi>Voice</hi> of the Almighty in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171426:19"/>
               <hi>Thunder,</hi> is, <hi>Admire the Goodness of God, and love such a God!</hi> It was said 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.14, 17, 20. <hi>The Lord thundered from Heaven, and the most high utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his voice:</hi> Well, at this time when the Thunder fell, what became of him? <hi>He sent from above, he took me; he delivered me, because he delighted in me—For I have kept the ways of the Lord, and have not wickedly departed from my God;</hi> and then saith he, <hi>Therefore I will give thanks unto thee, O Lord, among the Heathen, and I will sing praises unto thy Name.</hi> We are to sing Praises to the Name of that God who <hi>thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and doth not make us desolate. As for us, we are upon every provocation apt to call for <hi>fire from Heaven,</hi> that is, for <hi>Thunder,</hi> as the angry Disciples did: O! if God should by <hi>fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> consume us, as often as our sins call for it, what would become of us! It is then the voice of the <hi>Thunder, O the patience of God! How compassionate is he, he doth not make us perish from our way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>voice</hi> of God in the Thunder, is, <hi>speedily, presently, thoroughly, make your peace with God.</hi> When the <hi>thunder</hi> comes, at what rate is it? We have it in <hi>Psal.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Ʋpon the wicked he shall rain snares, fire and brimstone, and an horrible tempest.</hi> The <hi>thunder</hi> comes like <hi>snares</hi> upon them: This then is the voice of thunder, <hi>Oh, get out of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regeneracy immediately, lest the thunder of God ensnare you in that unregencracy!</hi> We see by <hi>thunder</hi> that Men go <hi>down in a moment to the grave:</hi> Therefore the <hi>voice</hi> of thunder is, <hi>O get into good terms with God, before such a moment comes, do it this very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Alas, when it thundereth, a man that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God in Christ, may say, <hi>What a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable man were I, if my great work were now to do!</hi> but when that is well done, let thunder come; a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171426:19"/>Pagan could say, <hi>He that is not conscious to himself of any fault, need not fear a Thunder-bolt.</hi> Well then, get rid of all thy <hi>sins,</hi> by a lively Faith in him that is the only <hi>Saviour</hi> of his People from their <hi>sins;</hi> that <hi>to live may be Christ, and to dye gain;</hi> this the <hi>thunder</hi> calleth for.</p>
            <p>§. The Second <hi>Admonition</hi> is, <hi>There is a mighty voice of the Almighty God, uttered like that of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in the wheels of Providence, that are now turning in the World.</hi> May I now do the part of a <hi>John Baptist,</hi> who said once, <hi>I am the voice of one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the people of God in the Wilderness.</hi> It is here said, <hi>there were voices,</hi> shall I now bring out those <hi>voices</hi> articulately to the Understanding of those whom I am addressing? We read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.3, 4. <hi>When</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ had <hi>cried with a loud voice, seven thunders uttered their voices.</hi> Truly, our Lord Jesus Christ has been <hi>crying with a loud voice,</hi> and <hi>thunders</hi> too have been uttering <hi>their voices</hi> among us. Indeed when <hi>John</hi> was about to write the <hi>voices</hi> of the <hi>thunders, he heard a voice from heaven, saying, write them not.</hi> But when I was about to bring the <hi>voices</hi> of our <hi>thunders</hi> to you, I had no such voice from the Lord, <hi>bring them not:</hi> No, his <hi>voice</hi> to me was, <hi>bring them out,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I shall bring them to you, had I <hi>a voice like thunder,</hi> there are seven Words which I should have to utter among you. Let it be demanded, what are the <hi>thundring voices</hi> that are at this day to be heard among the Nations? these <hi>voices</hi> we will run over them swiftly, like rapid <hi>thunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. The First <hi>Thundring voice</hi> of the Almighty unto us, is, <hi>Let not the unvaluable Ordinances of the Lord Jesus Christ be undervalued, lest the most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming Povidences of the Lord revenge that contempt.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171426:20"/>Do you ask where I heard this <hi>voice?</hi> how I learnt this voice? why, from the very <hi>Text</hi> I am upon. <hi>The Angel took the Censor, and filled it with fire of the Altar, and cast it into the Earth, and there were voices, and thunderings, and lightnings, and an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</hi> The <hi>Altar</hi> of God, at which the <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of God are celebrated, if once the things of that <hi>Altar</hi> come to be <hi>cast upon the earth,</hi> God hath fearful things to do against these <hi>people of the earth,</hi> where they shall be so abused. This is the <hi>warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing piece</hi> to be now fired off with <hi>thunder;</hi> Oh! let not the <hi>Earth</hi> so take you up, as to make you despise the <hi>Altar</hi> of God; be not so inchanted with the <hi>Earth,</hi> as to have no Communion with the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> of God. If Men grow weary of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> if Men grow careless of Ordinances, if Men grow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful under <hi>Ordinances,</hi> this is the <hi>voice</hi> to those Men, <hi>God hath Thunders, and Lightnings, and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in his Temple to bring upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. A Second <hi>Thundring voice</hi> from God is this, <hi>Let the Lord Jesus Christ be set upon his Throne, else that Lord of all will dart burning vengeance from his Throne.</hi> Would you know how I came at this <hi>voice?</hi> You may read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Out of the Throne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded lightnings, and hunderings, and voices.</hi> The <hi>voice</hi> unto you is about the <hi>Throne</hi> of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, <hi>O set him upon his Throne, else there will come thunders and lightnings upon you, from the Throne of his Glory.</hi> Let us <hi>exalt</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ, as the King of <hi>Sion,</hi> as the only <hi>Law-giver of his Church,</hi> and let us duly submit to all his Orders. Yea, let us have <hi>high thoughts</hi> of our Lord, and set him on a glorious high Throne. Could we hear the <hi>Angels</hi> of God speaking with their <hi>voices</hi> unto us, I know what they would say, their <hi>voices</hi> would
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171426:20"/>be, <hi>O little do ye think, what a Jesus our Jesus is! Why do not ye prize that Jesus, love that Jesus, serve that Jesus for ever?</hi> the Voice then is, Let us have such thoughts about our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>§. A Third <hi>Thundering voice</hi> is this, <hi>Let men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware exceedingly, beware continually, beware lest they wrong the Lord Jesus Christ before they are aware!</hi> How comes this to be among the <hi>voices?</hi> It was once thus, you find it spoke in <hi>thunder</hi> and <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Acts</hi> 22.7, 8. <hi>I heard a voice saying unto me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? And I answered, who art thou Lord? and he said unto me, I am Jesus of Nazareth whom thou persecutest.</hi> Truly so there is a <hi>voice</hi> from the Lord Jesus Christ unto us all, <hi>O see to it, that ye do not wrong me!</hi> His <hi>voice</hi> is, you wrong a <hi>Jesus,</hi> when you wrong those that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Jesus,</hi> those that resemble <hi>Jesus!</hi> ye wrong a <hi>Jesus,</hi> when ye persecute a Church of <hi>Jesus!</hi> you wrong a <hi>Jesus,</hi> when you neglect <hi>great Salvation</hi> of <hi>Jesus!</hi> This is the <hi>voice</hi> unto you from Heaven, see to it, that ye do not give <hi>unsuspected blows to the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> who can by <hi>thunder</hi> chastize those that give the blows.</p>
            <p>§. A Fourth <hi>voice</hi> as of <hi>thunder</hi> to us, is, <hi>The Lord is at hand! make ready every Soul, make ready for the appearance of the Lord.</hi> It was the Cry, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.6. <hi>There was a Cry made, Behold, the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cometh, go ye out to meet him.</hi> Even so there is a <hi>voice</hi> this day, and that is, <hi>The Lord is coming, be ready to meet him.</hi> It will not be <hi>long</hi> before the Lord Jesus Christ shall make his descent into our <hi>Air,</hi> it will not be <hi>long</hi> before the Lord Jesus Christ <hi>shall come, and he shall not keep silence, a fire shall devour before him;</hi> it will not be <hi>long,</hi> e're the Lord will come to <hi>judge the Earth with Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171426:21"/>and the People with Equity.</hi> There is a Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a thousand things advertising us, that his <hi>coming is at hand.</hi> Many particulars are considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and this among the rest. When a <hi>King</hi> is coming home, there is <hi>whispering</hi> among his Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick Servants that he is a coming; thus among the Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nts of our Lord there is a <hi>discoursing</hi> about the <hi>coming</hi> of the Lord, they who are not buried in the <hi>slumber,</hi> which alas, are to fetter you most in our days, are now much talking upon this, <hi>When will the Lord come, and what shall be the signs of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> The Voice about it is, <hi>I come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. A Fifth <hi>Voice</hi> is, as of <hi>Thunder</hi> unto us, <hi>woful, dolefull, dismal will be the day and the doom of all that shall shortly be found strangers to the Lord Jesus Christ: Let none of you be found in that wofull Number.</hi> Are you to seek for his <hi>Voice?</hi> It was said in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.14, 15 The <hi>Second Wo is past, and behold the Third Wo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth quickly.</hi> Why? the <hi>great voices in Heaven</hi> are going to <hi>sound, with the Thunder</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Angel,</hi> and there is a <hi>voice</hi> to be made on <hi>Earth</hi> about it. It will be a <hi>Woful Trumpet</hi> unto the Wicked that is now going to sound. The <hi>voices</hi> now are, shortly <hi>Wo</hi> to all the Prophane, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the Cursing, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the Swearing, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the Wanton, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the Fraudulent, <hi>Wo</hi> to all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable. Yea, and there are other Wicked ones, not so grosly Wicked. 'Tis said, <hi>God shall turn all the Wicked into Hell, and all that forget him.</hi> Very shortly <hi>Wo</hi> will be to all <hi>Prayerless</hi> Persons, for they are the <hi>Forgetters of God? Wo</hi> to all that are so taken up with the things of this <hi>World,</hi> who are so busie, zealous and eager therein, that they hardly ever once a Week Pray before the God of Heaven. These <hi>Woes</hi> are now a going thro' the Earth, to make
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171426:21"/>a rueful rack among such, and all such as have no Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in the Precious Lord Jesus Christ. There was once a <hi>voice, an Ark! an Ark! for a drowning Wretch!</hi> so I say now, and Oh! could I speak it with a voice of Thunder, <hi>a Christ, a Christ, for a Perishing Soul! Wo</hi> to that Soul that prefers a <hi>Lust</hi> above a <hi>Christ,</hi> at such a day as this.</p>
            <p>§. A sixth <hi>voice,</hi> equal to any <hi>Thunders,</hi> is, <hi>All Rotten secret Hypocrites among Fair Professors, will most mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly be most miserable Creatures: Take heed of being among those Miserables.</hi> Are you at a loss what we have to form this <hi>voice?</hi> You have it in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. he that was a <hi>voice,</hi> did there say of the Lord, <hi>He will thoroughly purge his floor, and gather his Wheat into the garner, but he will burn up the Chaff with unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Fire.</hi> This I say, with as Penetrating a <hi>voice</hi> as I can, <hi>this</hi> take; take it as a <hi>voice</hi> from Heaven; <hi>That the Lord is quickly upon doing some very strange things to purge his Church.</hi> There are <hi>Hypocrites</hi> in the most Holy Societies, and such as indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the vilest of Impieties; but the Lord is just going to do such <hi>Men-discovering</hi> things, as will strangely make the Churches know <hi>that he searcheth the hearts and the reins; such men-distinguishing things</hi> as will separate <hi>the Precious from the vile.</hi> As we read of Old, when <hi>Thunders</hi> fell upon the <hi>Assyrian</hi> Camp, <hi>Fear surprized the Hypocorites in Sion:</hi> So those Voices are now to be heard as might justly Smite the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> with a fearful amazement of Soul!</p>
            <p>§. But Lastly, the <hi>Seventh voice,</hi> which I am to utter like <hi>Thunder</hi> among you, is, <hi>The Everlasting Gospel is Preached among You; O do not slight that Gospel!</hi> There was a <hi>voice</hi> once in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.7. <hi>An Angel flew in the midst of Heaven, having the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171426:22"/>Gospel to Preach, and he said with a loud voice, Fear God, and give Glory to him, for the hour of his Judgment is come.</hi> Thus I say with a <hi>loud voice;</hi> I have here the <hi>Everlasting Gospel</hi> in my hand, this <hi>Gospel</hi> that has been Preached to you, hath come like <hi>Thunder</hi> upon your Souls full many a time. Well, the <hi>voice</hi> is, if this Gospel be slighted, that God that hath lately visited <hi>my House</hi> with his <hi>Thunder,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hurting any thing, may bring <hi>worse Thunders</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Souls of those that shall tread under foot this Gospel, that is brought unto them in this. Disobey this <hi>Gospel,</hi> and what will follow? There is no <hi>Thunder</hi> like that, <hi>Let never fruit be found on that Soul!</hi> No thunder like that, <hi>He that is Ʋnjust, let him be Ʋnjust still! he that is filthy, let him be filthy still! Spiritual Plagues,</hi> none are so Thunder-struck as those that are struck by such <hi>Plagues.</hi> Now, what if God for the slighting of his <hi>Gospel,</hi> cause these <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to fall upon you, I say then, Here is the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; O embrace the Jesus Christ that is offered in the Gospel! Receive the <hi>Blood</hi> offered in this <hi>Gospel!</hi> Receive the <hi>Grace</hi> offered in this <hi>Gospel!</hi> This <hi>Gospel</hi> with the New-<hi>Covenant,</hi> the Gospel-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the <hi>Blood,</hi> and the <hi>Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Christ</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> has been brought you many a time: Oh! Give the consent of your Souls to it. The <hi>voice</hi> of the Lord from Heaven, is, <hi>Shall I save thee according to this Covenant? Shall I rule thee according to this Covenant? Shall my Spirit lead thee according to this Covenant? According to this Covenant, shall I give thee Grace and Glory, and every good thing?</hi> O Reply, <hi>My God, I do consent!</hi> and say it with a serious <hi>voice,</hi> a sincere <hi>voice;</hi> and so God will say with a Kind <hi>voice, These are dear Children, and I will surely have Mercy on Them!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>
            <hi>FINIS.</hi>
            <pb facs="tcp:171426:22"/>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>